export const BIOLOGYA2015 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Which of the following organisms is not a protozoan?",
A: "amoeba",
B: "ascaris",
C: "plasmodium",
D: "paramecium",
answer: "B. ascaris",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The structure of the cell membrane is a",
A: "double layer and a double protein layer",
B: "middle bi-layer of protein with a lipid layer on either surface",
C: "middle bi-layer of lipid with a protein layer on either surface",
D: "protein layer with two inner lipid layers",
answer: "C. middle bi-layer of lipid with a protein layer on either surface",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. Which of the following cells is a specialized cell?",
A: "amoeba",
B: "plasmodium",
C: "guard cell",
D: "meristematic cell",
answer: "C. guard cell",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The following organisms have structures for movement except",
A: "amoeba",
B: "spirogyra",
C: "volvox",
D: "paramecium",
answer: "B. spirogyra",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. Which of the following statements about the protoplasm of a cell is not correct? It",
A: "is a gelatinous mass",
B: "consists of cytoplasm and nucleus",
C: "is the liquid part of the nucleus",
D: "contains cellular organelles",
answer: "B. consists of cytoplasm and nucleus",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. When a spirogyra filament is placed in a concentrated salt solution for 30 minutes, the cell would become",
A: "plasmolysed",
B: "turgid",
C: "shortened",
D: "elongated",
answer: "A. plasmolysed",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Which of the labelled parts enable the animal to stay under water most of the time?",
A: "l, IV and V",
B: "l, Il and V",
C: "l, Ill and IV",
D: "Ill, IV and V",
answer: "B. l, Il and V",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Two characteristic features of the class to which the crocodile belongs are labelled",
A: "I and Il",
B: "Ill and IV",
C: "Il and IV",
D: "Il and V",
answer: "B. Ill and IV",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Water and salts are both lost from the human body in",
A: "breath and sweat",
B: "breath and urine",
C: "breath, urine and sweat",
D: "sweat and urine",
answer: "D. sweat and urine",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Which of the following features could be used to determine the growth of a seedling?",
A: "number of flowers",
B: "number of leaves",
C: "length of flowers",
D: "length of radicle",
answer: "D. length of radicle",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. In which of the following cells is the division likely to take place?",
A: "sperm cell",
B: "blood cell",
C: "muscle cell",
D: "uterine cell",
answer: "C. muscle cell",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. A plant that commonly undergoes vegetative propagation by means of leaves is",
A: "Hibiscus",
B: "Bryophylum",
C: "Crotalaria",
D: "Spirogyra",
answer: "B. Bryophylum",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. The part of the mammalian skeleton illustrated is the",
A: "atlas",
B: "axis vertebrae",
C: "cervical vertebrae",
D: "thoracic vertebrae",
answer: "C. cervical vertebrae",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The function of the part I is to",
A: "provide support to the spinal cord",
B: "provide surface for attachment of the muscle",
C: "carry the spinal cord",
D: "articulate with adjacent vertebrae",
answer: "C. carry the spinal cord",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Blood pressure is higher in the arteries as a result of",
A: "stress",
B: "contraction and relaxation",
C: "blockage in the arteries",
D: "pressure of valves",
answer: "B. contraction and relaxation",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. A farmer who wants to keep seeds for three years before planting and wants to prevent them from sprouting out uses",
A: "auxin",
B: "gibberellins",
C: "abscisin",
D: "cytokinins",
answer: "C. abscisin",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. A person had an accident that affected the skull but not the nose and later lost the sense of smell. The accident must have affected the",
A: "nose by extension",
B: "olfactory lobes of the brain",
C: "passages from the nose to the brain",
D: "part of the skull near the nose",
answer: "B. olfactory lobes of the brain",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. Ability of the human eye to focus images accurately on the retina is called",
A: "astigmatism",
B: "myopia",
C: "adjustment",
D: "accommodation",
answer: "D. accommodation",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Which of the following characteristic features is not associated with monocotyledonous plants?",
A: "well differentiated sepals and petals",
B: "presence of fibrous root system",
C: "presence of narrow leaves",
D: "floral parts are in multiples of three",
answer: "A. well differentiated sepals and petals",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The main difference between a seed and a fruit is that a fruit",
A: "is large while a seed is small",
B: "has two scars while a seed has one",
C: "is pigmented while a seed is not",
D: "can be dispersed by animals while a seed cannot",
answer: "B. has two scars while a seed has one",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Which of the following processes removes carbon (IV) oxide from the atmosphere?",
A: "Burning fuels",
B: "Putrefaction",
C: "Photosynthesis",
D: "Respiration in Plants",
answer: "C. Photosynthesis",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Why did the student add the dilute hydrochloric acid to the sugar solution in step II? To",
A: "oxidize the sugar solution",
B: "hydrolyse the sugar solution",
C: "dry the sugar solution",
D: "increase the volume of the sugar solution",
answer: "B. hydrolyse the sugar solution",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. What is the importance of step II in the testing process? To",
A: "neutralize the sugar solution",
B: "soften the sugar solution",
C: "change the colour of the sugar solution",
D: "increase the acid content of the sugar solution",
answer: "A. neutralize the sugar solution",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The colour change to be observed in step IV",
A: "blue-black",
B: "brick red",
C: "purple",
D: "violet",
answer: "B. brick red",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Which of the following organs of the alimentary canal is not correctly matched with its function?",
A: "Gall bladder - stores bile",
B: "Liver - stores glycogen",
C: "Appendix - releases enzymes",
D: "Teeth - grind food",
answer: "C. Appendix - releases enzymes",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. A person suffering from obstruction of the bile duct is advised not to eat fats and oil because",
A: "bile digests fats and oil",
B: "fats and oil can only be absorbed when bile is absent",
C: "bile emulsifies fats and oil",
D: "bile adds water to digesting food",
answer: "C. bile emulsifies fats and oil",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. A community reaches a climax when",
A: "only pioneer organisms are present",
B: "new habitats are constantly being formed",
C: "there is an introduction of new plants and animal species within the community",
D: "the composition and size of a community remain constant over a long period",
answer: "D. the composition and size of a community remain constant over a long period",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Which of the following components make up an ecosystem?",
A: "decomposers, animals and non-living factors",
B: "living and non-living factors",
C: "plants and non-living factors",
D: "plants, decomposers and non-living factors",
answer: "B. living and non-living factors",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. The major problem experienced by organisms living in small water bodies",
A: "drying up",
B: "oxygen deficiency",
C: "scarcity of food",
D: "wave action",
answer: "A. drying up",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. The capillarity of a soil refers",
A: "the particle size of soil",
B: "how easily water passes through soil",
C: "how well water rises up in soil",
D: "proportion of water a soil holds",
answer: "C. how well water rises up in soil",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. An organism at the start of a food chain which provides the total input of energy into an ecosystem is the",
A: "sun",
B: "producer",
C: "consumer",
D: "decomposer",
answer: "B. producer",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. The mode of nutrition of the plant in the diagram is",
A: "photosynthetic and chemosynthetic",
B: "saprophytic and carnivorous",
C: "photosynthetic and carnivorous",
D: "chemosynthetic and saprophytic",
answer: "C. photosynthetic and carnivorous",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. The structure labelled I is",
A: "a pitcher",
B: "an onion",
C: "a flower",
D: "a tendril",
answer: "A. a pitcher",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. In which type of soil is the plant found? Soil that is",
A: "poorly aerated",
B: "water logged",
C: "exposed",
D: "nitrogen deficient",
answer: "B. water logged",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. Which of the following organisms is an endoparasite?",
A: "Tapeworm",
B: "Flea",
C: "Tick",
D: "Aphid",
answer: "A. Tapeworm",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Oil applied to the surface of water kills the larvae of mosquitoes through",
A: "dehydration",
B: "poisoning",
C: "starvation",
D: "suffocation",
answer: "D. suffocation",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Which of the following natural resources is most readily available to all organisms?",
A: "Oil",
B: "Water",
C: "Air",
D: "Food",
answer: "C. Air",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Which of the following resources is non-renewable?",
A: "Forest reserve",
B: "Mineral deposit",
C: "Water",
D: "Wild life",
answer: "B. Mineral deposit",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Soil erosion could be prevented by",
A: "flooding a farmland",
B: "cover-cropping",
C: "deforestation",
D: "leaving the soil bare",
answer: "B. cover-cropping",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Which of the following statements about human blood groups is not true?",
A: "A is dominant over B",
B: "O is recessive",
C: "B is dominant over O",
D: "A and B are co-dominant",
answer: "A. A is dominant over B",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Which of the following traits is not inheritable? Ability to",
A: "taste PTC",
B: "roll the tongue",
C: "move the ear",
D: "roll the eyeball",
answer: "D. roll the eyeball",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. A woman with blood group A gives birth to a child with blood group O. Which of the following blood groups cannot belong to the father?",
A: "A",
B: "B",
C: "AB",
D: "O",
answer: "C. AB",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. How many chromosomes will be in a gamete if the normal cell has four chromosomes?",
A: "2",
B: "4",
C: "6",
D: "8",
answer: "A. 2",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. Which of the following statements about the cross is correct?",
A: "The gene for the spotted coat is recessive to the gene for the black coat",
B: "Black coat and spotted coat are co-dominant",
C: "The gene for the spotted coat is dominant over the gene for the black coat",
D: "The genotype for the F1 are homozygous dominant",
answer: "C. The gene for the spotted coat is dominant over the gene for the black coat",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. What are the genotypes of the parents if the gene for skin colour is H",
A: "zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz",
B: "zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz",
C: "zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz",
D: "zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz",
answer: "A. HH 46. hh",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. According to Mendel's first law of inheritance, segregation of genes occur when",
A: "tall plants are crossbred",
B: "short plants are crossbred",
C: "tall plants and short plants are crossbred",
D: "plants are crossbred",
answer: "C. tall plants and short plants are crossbred",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. Which of the following statements about sex-linked characters is not true?",
A: "They are usually borne on the X chromosome",
B: "They are more common in males",
C: "Males are usually carriers",
D: "They are not usually carried on the Y chromosomes",
answer: "C. Males are usually carriers",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Which of the varieties is likely to decrease most in number if a predatory fish is introduced into the river?",
A: "P",
B: "Q",
C: "R",
D: "S",
answer: "C. R",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Which of the varieties is most likely to outlive the others?",
A: "P",
B: "Q",
C: "R",
D: "S",
answer: "D. S",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. The variety selected in question 49 will outlive the others because the",
A: "variety is the most beautiful",
B: "variety does not have markings",
C: "markings of the variety are similar to those of the environment",
D: "predator does not like eating the variety",
answer: "C. markings of the variety are similar to those of the environment",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},


]